





C V n CURRÍCULUM VÍTAE NORMALIZADO



Filippo Bistaffa

Generated from: Editor CVN de FECYT Date of document: 15/12/2017

v 1.4.0

dbc1854042762419b6d7cee7227f381c

This electronic file (PDF) has embedded CVN technology (CVN-XML). The CVN technology of this file allows you to export and import curricular data from and to any compatible data base. List of adapted databases available at: http://cvn.fecyt.es/





Summary of CV

This section describes briefly a summary of your career in science, academic and research; the main scientific and technological achievements and goals in your line of research in the medium -and long- term. It also includes other important aspects or peculiarities.

I received the Ph.D. degree in computer science from the University of Verona, Italy, in 2016. I am currently a Marie Skłodowska-Curie Fellow at IIIA-CSIC, as part of a H2020-MSCA-IF-2016-funded project entitled "Collectiveware: Highly-parallel algorithms for collective intelligence". My research focuses on multi-agent systems, a theoretic model used to describe and solve problems in many real-world scenarios, including collective energy purchasing and ridesharing. The complex dynamics among the large number of entities in these systems usually result in very hard optimisation problems. My research aims at dealing with this complexity, both from a theoretical perspective (proposing novel algorithms and models) and from a practical one, using Graphics Processing Units (GPUs) to speed-up the execution of algorithms used to compute the solutions.





Filippo Bistaffa

Surname(s): Bistaffa
Name: Filippo
Passport: YA5165133

ORCID: **0000-0003-1658-6125**

Date of birth:

Gender:

Nationality:

Country of birth:

Aut. region/reg. of birth:

Contact province:

City of birth:

Bovolone

Contact address: IIIA-CSIC, Campus UAB

Rest of contact address:

Postcode:

Contact country:

Contact aut. region/reg.:

Contact city:

Room 314

08193

Spain

Catalonia

Catalonia

Cerdanyola

Email: filippo.bistaffa@iiia.csic.es
Personal web page: https://filippobistaffa.github.io

Current professional situation

Employing entity: Instituto de Investigación en Type of entity: State agency

Inteligencia Artificial

Professional category: Marie Skłodowska-Curie Fellow

Start date: 16/06/2017

Type of contract: Grant-assisted student (pre or Dedication regime: Full time

post-doctoral, others)

Primary (UNESCO code): 330411 - Computing systems design

Performed tasks: Main researcher for project "Collectiveware: Highly-Parallel Algorithms for Collective

Intelligence" (H2020-MSCA-IF-2016 HPA4CF)

Previous positions and activities

Employing entity	Professional category	Start date
University of Verona	Research associate	01/01/2016

Employing entity: University of Verona **Type of entity:** University

Professional category: Research associate

Start-End date: 01/01/2016 - 30/06/2017 **Duration:** 1 year - 6 months







Education

University education

1st and 2nd cycle studies and pre-Bologna degrees

1 University degree: Higher degree

Name of qualification: M.Sc. Engineering and Computer Science

Degree awarding entity: University of Verona

Date of qualification: 22/03/2012

Average mark: Excellent

2 University degree: Middle degree

Name of qualification: B.Sc. Computer Engineering

Degree awarding entity: University of Pavia

Date of qualification: 15/09/2009

Average mark: Excellent

Doctorates

Doctorate programme: Computer Science

Degree awarding entity: University of Verona Type of entity: University

Date of degree: 22/04/2016 European doctorate: Yes

Thesis title: Constraint Optimisation Techniques for Real-World Applications

Thesis director: Alessandro Farinelli

Language skills

Language	Listening skills	Reading skills	Spoken interaction	Speaking skills	Writing skills
Spanish	A2	A2	A2	A2	A2
English	C2	C2	C2	C2	C2
Italian	C2	C2	C2	C2	C2

Teaching experience







General teaching experience

1 Name of the course: Algorithms (Programming Laboratory II)

University degree: Bioinformatics

Start date: 01/10/2015 End date: 30/06/2016
Entity: University of Verona Type of entity: University

Faculty, institute or centre: Department of Computer Science

2 Name of the course: Algorithms (Programming Laboratory II)

University degree: Bioinformatics

Start date: 01/10/2013 End date: 30/06/2014 Entity: University of Verona Type of entity: University

Faculty, institute or centre: Department of Computer Science

Experience supervising doctoral thesis and/or final year projects

Project title: Forming Groups for Social Ridesharing with Time Constraints (MSc Thesis)

Entity: University of Verona

Type of entity: University

Student: Francesco Donato **Date of reading:** 15/03/2015

Scientific and technological experience

Scientific or technological activities

R&D projects funded through competitive calls of public or private entities

Name of the project: Collectiveware: Highly-parallel algorithms for collective intelligence
Entity where project took place: Instituto de
Type of entity: State agency

Investigación en Inteligencia Artificial

Name principal investigator (PI, Co-PI....): Juan A. Rodríguez-Aguilar

N° of researchers: 1 Funding entity or bodies:

Marie Sklodowska-Curie Fellowship (European

Commission)

Start-End date: 16/06/2017 - 16/06/2019

Total amount: 158.121,6 €

2 Name of the project: Development of AI models and techniques for sustainable commuting

Entity where project took place: University of Type of entity: University

Verona

City of entity: Verona, Veneto, Italy

Name principal investigator (PI, Co-PI....): Alessandro Farinelli

Nº of researchers: 1





Type of entity: Public Research Body

Start-End date: 01/01/2016 - 30/06/2017

Total amount: 29.000 €

Scientific and technological activities

Scientific production

Publications, scientific and technical documents

Filippo Bistaffa; Alessandro Farinelli; Georgios Chalkiadakis; Sarvapali D Ramchurn. A Cooperative Game-Theoretic Approach to the Social Ridesharing Problem. Artificial Intelligence. 246, pp. 86 - 117. Elsevier, 2017. Available on-line at: http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0004370217300243.

DOI: 10.1016/j.artint.2017.02.004

Type of production: Scientific paper Format: Journal

Corresponding author: Yes

Alessandro Farinelli; Manuele Bicego; Filippo Bistaffa; Sarvapali D. Ramchurn. A Hierarchical Clustering Approach to Large-scale Near-optimal Coalition Formation with Quality Guarantees. International Scientific Journal Engineering Applications of Artificial Intelligence. 59, pp. 170 - 185. Elsevier, 2017. Available on-line at: http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0952197616302536.

DOI: 10.1016/j.engappai.2016.12.018

Type of production: Scientific paper Format: Journal

Corresponding author: No

3 Filippo Bistaffa; Alessandro Farinelli; Jesús Cerquides; Juan A. Rodríguez-Aguilar; Sarvapali D. Ramchurn. Algorithms for Graph-Constrained Coalition Formation in the Real World. ACM Transactions on Intelligent Systems and Technology. 8 - 4, ACM, 2017.

DOI: 10.1145/3040967

Type of production: Scientific paper Format: Journal

Corresponding author: Yes

4 Michele Roncalli; Filippo Bistaffa; Alessandro Farinelli. Decentralized Power Distribution in the Smart Grid with Ancillary Lines. Mobile Networks and Applications. pp. 1 - 9. Springer, 2017. Available on-line at: https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11036-017-0893-y.

DOI: 10.1007/s11036-017-0893-y

Type of production: Scientific paper Format: Journal

Corresponding author: No

Filippo Bistaffa; Nicola Bombieri; Alessandro Farinelli. An Efficient Approach for Accelerating Bucket Elimination on GPUs. IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics. In press, pp. 1 - 13. IEEE, 2016. Available on-line at: http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/7536134/.

DOI: 10.1109/TCYB.2016.2593773

Type of production: Scientific paper Format: Journal

Corresponding author: Yes







Works submitted to national or international conferences

Title of the work: CUBE: A CUDA Approach for Bucket Elimination on GPUs
Name of the conference: European Conference on Artificial Intelligence (Rank A)

Type of event: Conference Corresponding author: Yes

City of event: The Hague, Zuid-Holland, Holland

Date of event: 29/08/2016

Type of contribution: Scientific book or monograph

Filippo Bistaffa; Nicola Bombieri; Alessandro Farinelli. pp. 125 - 132. 2016. Available on-line at:

http://ebooks.iospress.nl/publication/44750>.

DOI: 10.3233/978-1-61499-672-9-125

Title of the work: Recommending Fair Payments for Large-Scale Social Ridesharing Name of the conference: ACM Conference on Recommender Systems (Rank B)

Type of event: Conference Corresponding author: Yes City of event: Vienna, Austria Date of event: 16/09/2015 Organising entity: ACM

Type of contribution: Scientific book or monograph

Filippo Bistaffa; Alessandro Farinelli; Georgios Chalkiadakis; Sarvapali D. Ramchurn. pp. 139 - 146.

Available on-line at: http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?doid=2792838.2800177.

DOI: 10.1145/2792838.2800177

3 Title of the work: Sharing Rides with Friends: a Coalition Formation Algorithm for Ridesharing

Name of the conference: AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (Rank A*)

Type of event: Conference Corresponding author: Yes

City of event: Austin, United States of America

Date of event: 25/01/2015 **Organising entity:** AAAI

Type of contribution: Scientific book or monograph

Filippo Bistaffa; Alessandro Farinelli; Sarvapali D. Ramchurn. pp. 608 - 614. 2015. Available on-line at:

http://www.aaai.org/ocs/index.php/AAAI/AAAI15/paper/view/9622.

4 Title of the work: Optimising Memory Management for Belief Propagation in Junction Trees using GPGPUs

Name of the conference: IEEE International Conference on Parallel and Distributed Systems (Park R)

Name of the conference: IEEE International Conference on Parallel and Distributed Systems (Rank B)

Type of event: Conference Corresponding author: Yes City of event: Hsinchu, Taiwan Date of event: 16/12/2014 Organising entity: IEEE

Type of contribution: Scientific book or monograph

Filippo Bistaffa; Alessandro Farinelli; Nicola Bombieri. pp. 526 - 533. 2014. Available on-line at:

http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/7097850>.

DOI: 10.1109/padsw.2014.7097850







5 Title of the work: Anytime Coalition Structure Generation on Synergy Graphs

Name of the conference: International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multiagent Systems (Rank

A*)

Type of event: Conference Corresponding author: Yes

City of event: Paris, Île de France, France

Date of event: 05/05/2014 **Organising entity:** IFAAMAS

Type of contribution: Scientific book or monograph

Filippo Bistaffa; Alessandro Farinelli; Jesús Cerquides; Juan Rodríguez-Aguilar; Sarvapali D. Ramchurn. pp.

13 - 20. 2014. Available on-line at: http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2615737.

Title of the work: Anytime Coalition Structure Generation on Scale-Free and Community Networks Name of the conference: International Joint Workshop on Optimisation in Multiagent Systems and

Distributed Constraint Reasoning (Rank W)

Type of event: Workshop Corresponding author: Yes

City of event: Paris, Île de France, France

Date of event: 05/05/2014 **Organising entity:** IFAAMAS

Type of contribution: Scientific book or monograph

Filippo Bistaffa; Alessandro Farinelli; Jesús Cerquides; Juan Rodríguez-Aguilar; Sarvapali D. Ramchurn.

2014.

7 Title of the work: Parallel Algorithms for Hard Combinatorial Optimisation Problems in Multi-Agent Systems

(Doctoral Consortium)

Name of the conference: International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multiagent Systems (Rank

A*)

Corresponding author: Yes

City of event: Paris, Île de France, France

Date of event: 05/05/2014 **Organising entity:** IFAAMAS

Type of contribution: Scientific book or monograph

Filippo Bistaffa. pp. 1717 - 1718. Available on-line at: http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2616142.

8 Title of the work: A Fast Approach to Form Core-Stable Coalitions Based on a Dynamic Model

Name of the conference: IEEE International Joint Conferences on Web Intelligence and Intelligent Agent

Technologies (Rank B)

Type of event: Conference

Corresponding author: Yes

City of event: Atlanta, United States of America

Date of event: 17/11/2013 **Organising entity:** IEEE

Type of contribution: Scientific book or monograph

Filippo Bistaffa; Alessandro Farinelli. pp. 122 - 129. 2013. Available on-line at:

http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/6690780.

DOI: 10.1109/WI-IAT.2013.100

9 Title of the work: Coalitional Energy Purchasing in the Smart Grid

Name of the conference: IEEE International Energy Conference & Exhibition

Type of event: Conference Corresponding author: No







City of event: Firenze, Toscana, Italy

Date of event: 09/09/2012 Organising entity: IEEE

Type of contribution: Scientific book or monograph

Meritxell Vinyals; Filippo Bistaffa; Alessandro Farinelli; Alex Rogers. pp. 848 - 853. 2012. Available on-line

at: http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/6348270>.

DOI: 10.1109/energycon.2012.6348270

10 Title of the work: Decentralised Stable Coalition Formation Among Energy Consumers in the Smart Grid

(demonstration)

Name of the conference: International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multiagent Systems (Rank

A*)

Type of event: Conference Corresponding author: Yes

City of event: Valencia, Valencian Community, Spain

Date of event: 04/06/2012 **Organising entity:** IFAAMAS

Type of contribution: Scientific book or monograph

Filippo Bistaffa; Alessandro Farinelli; Meritxell Vinyals; Alex Rogers. pp. 1461 - 1462. 2012. Available on-line

at: http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2344061>.

11 Title of the work: Stable Coalition Formation Among Energy Consumers in the Smart Grid

Name of the conference: International Workshop on Agent Technologies for Energy Systems (Rank W)

Corresponding author: No

City of event: Valencia, Valencian Community, Spain

Date of event: 04/06/2012 Organising entity: IFAAMAS

Type of contribution: Scientific book or monograph

Meritxell Vinyals; Filippo Bistaffa; Alessandro Farinelli; Alex Rogers. 2012.

R&D management and participation in scientific committees

Organization of R&D activities

- 1 Title of the activity: Program chair for AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence, AAAI (A*)
- 2 Title of the activity: Program chair for European Conference on Artificial Intelligence, ECAI (A)
- **Title of the activity:** Program chair for International Joint Conference Conference on Artificial Intelligence, IJCAI (A*)
- **Title of the activity:** Program chair for International Workshop on Optimisation in Multiagent Systems, OptMAS







- 5 Title of the activity: Program chair for International Workshop on Teams in Multiagent Systems, TEAMAS
- **6** Title of the activity: Reviewer for Artificial Intelligence, AIJ (Q1)
- 7 Title of the activity: Reviewer for IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics, IEEE CYB (Q1)
- **8** Title of the activity: Reviewer for RoboCup International Symposium

Other achievements

Stays in public or private R&D centres

1 Entity: University of Southampton Type of entity: University

Faculty, institute or centre: ECS Department

City of entity: Southampton, Hampshire and Isle of Wight, United Kingdom

Start-End date: 01/06/2014 - 31/03/2015

Goals of the stay: Guest

Provable tasks: Research of AI methods for sustainable urban commuting

2 Entity: IIIA-CSIC Type of entity: University Research Institute

City of entity: Barcelona, Catalonia, Spain Start-End date: 01/06/2013 - 30/06/2013

Goals of the stay: Guest

Provable tasks: Research of Al methods for collective formation

Obtained grants and scholarships

1 Name of the grant: H2020-MSCA-IF-2016 (158.121 EUR)

Aims: Post-doctoral

Awarding entity: Comisión EuropeaType of entity: EUConferral date: 16/06/2017Duration: 2 years

End date: 15/06/2019

Entity where activity was carried out: Instituto de Investigación en Inteligencia Artificial

2 Name of the grant: Doctoral grant (~41.000 EUR)

Awarding entity: Cariverona Foundation

Conferral date: 01/01/2013 Duration: 3 years

End date: 31/12/2015

Entity where activity was carried out: University of Verona Faculty, institute or centre: Department of Computer Science







3 Name of the grant: Juan de la Cierva (50.000 EUR, renunciado)

Aims: Post-doctoral

Awarding entity: Ministerio de Ciencia e Innovación Type of entity: State agency



